<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="home">
    <p>TEI Lex-0 is both a technical specification and a set of community-based recommendations for
        encoding machine-readable dictionaries. It helps you create, analyze, and share lexical
        resources that are interoperable, sustainable, and fit for purpose.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#Johnson1775"
        rend="unwrapped tb-floated tb-smaller">
        <xi:include href="../examples/examples.stripped.xml" corresp="../examples/examples.xml"
            xpointer="SJ.DEL"/>
    </egXML>
    <div xml:id="home.quickstart">
        <head>Quickstart</head>
        <p>To start using Lex-0 in your projects, you'll need a schema-aware XML editor and one of
            our schemas: <list>
                <item>
                    <ref target="schema/lex0.rng">Relax NG (RNG)</ref>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <ref target="#">RELAX NG Compact (coming soon)</ref>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <ref target="#">XML Schema (XSD) (coming soon)</ref>
                </item>
            </list></p>
        <p>If you are new to the world of TEI and XML, in general, or need a refresher on how to
            validate TEI files, see <ref target="#faq.get-started">FAQ → Getting Started</ref></p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="home.howTo">
        <head>How to use the <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi></head>
        <p>The <hi rend="bold">narrative</hi> chapters of these <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi>
            explain <hi rend="italic">why</hi> TEI Lex-0 recommends certain practices, <hi
                rend="italic">what</hi> those practices mean for lexicographic work, and <hi
                rend="italic">how</hi> to apply them in real encoding situations. Each chapter
            focuses on a specific type of lexicographic content, covering rationale, examples and
            guidance for the consistent encoding of <ref target="#entries">entries</ref>, <ref
                target="#forms">forms</ref>, <ref target="#senses">senses</ref>, <ref
                target="#translations">translations</ref>, <ref target="#cross-references"
                >cross-references</ref> and <ref target="#usage">usage labels</ref>.</p>
        <p>The <hi rend="bold">technical</hi>
            <ref target="#specification">Specification</ref> is the <hi rend="italic">reference
                manual</hi> (and, effectively, the “grammar”) of Lex-0. When you need to answer
            concrete questions like “What elements are allowed within <gi>sense</gi>?”, “Which
            attributes are permitted on <gi>form</gi>?”, or “What types of values are valid in
                <att>target</att>?”, the <hi rend="italic">Specification</hi> is the first place to
            look. </p>
        <p>The chapter on the <ref target="#community">Community</ref> explains how TEI Lex-0
            evolved and the people behind it, while <ref target="#faq">FAQs</ref> provide quick
            answers on <ref target="#faq.whyLex-0">why</ref> Lex-0 exists, <ref
                target="#faq.lex-0-vs-TEI">how</ref> it relates to TEI P5, and how to <ref
                target="#faq.get-started">get started</ref> with validation and tooling. They also
            cover issues such as where to <ref target="#faq.who-to-ask">ask questions</ref>, how to
                <ref target="#faq.how-to-contribute">get involved</ref> with the development, how
                <ref target="#faq.how-to-cite">to cite</ref> the <hi rend="italic">Guidelines</hi>
            etc.</p>
    </div>
    <divGen type="revision-history"/>
</div>