<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei_oxygen.css"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei.lex0.odd.css"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xml:id="introduction">
    <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>TEI Lex-0 is both a technical specification and a set of community-based recommendations
            for encoding machine-readable dictionaries. It is rooted in the <ref
                target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html"> Guidelines
                of the Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (TEI) and delivered as a customization of the
            TEI schema.</p>
        <p>Following the spirit of TEI Analytics, developed in the context of the MONK project <ref
                type="cit" target="#Zillig2009">(Zillig 2009)</ref>, TEI Lex-0 aims at establishing
            a baseline encoding and a target format to facilitate the interoperability of
            heterogeneously encoded lexical resources. This is important both in the context of
            building lexical infrastructures as such <ref type="cit" target="#Ermolaev2012"
                >(Ermolaev and Tasovac 2012)</ref> and in the context of developing generic
            TEI-aware tools such as dictionary viewers and profilers. </p>
        <p>For the latest changes, see our <ref target="#revisionHistory">revision
            history</ref>.</p>
    <div xml:id="introduction.guidelines">
        <head>The Guidelines</head>
        <p>To what extent can we achieve consistent encoding within a given community of practice by
            following the TEI Guidelines? The topic is of particular importance for lexical data if
            we think of the potential wealth of content we could gain from pooling together the
            information available in the variety of highly structured, historical and contemporary
            lexical resources. The encoding possibilities offered by the Dictionaries Chapter in the
            Guidelines are too numerous and too flexible to guarantee sufficient interoperability
            and a coherent model for searching, visualising or enriching multiple lexical
            resources.</p>
        
    
        <!-- <p>TODO: How to use these guidelines. </p>-->
        <divGen type="how-to-cite"/>
        <divGen type="revision-history"/>
    </div>
   
      
       
</div>
