<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>A <hi rend="italic">model class</hi> is a named group of elements that can be used in
            the same structural positions. Model classes do not appear in your XML as tags; you
            never write a model class in the document. Instead, they are part of the architecture
            behind the scenes.</p>
         <p>You will most often encounter model classes when you are trying to understand a content
            model and you see something like <q>members of class X</q>. When that happens, you can
            look up the model class, read which elements belong to it, and return to the original
            element’s content model and interpret it as: <q>you may use one of these elements
               here</q>.</p>
         <p>In practical terms, however, most lexicographers and encoders will <hi rend="italic"
               >not</hi> spend much time investigating or thinking about model classes. In
            day-to-day work, it is much more important for you to focus on individual elements,
            their attributes, and what other concrete elements are allowed within the given element.
            For instance, you cannot have a <ref target="TEI.def.html">&lt;def&gt;</ref> within a
               <ref target="TEI.sense.html">&lt;sense&gt;</ref>, but you can have a <ref
               target="TEI.cit.html">&lt;cit&gt;</ref> within a <ref target="TEI.sense.html"
               >&lt;sense&gt;</ref>, and within <ref target="TEI.cit.html">&lt;cit&gt;</ref>, you
            can have a <ref target="TEI.def.html">&lt;def&gt;</ref>. Model classes make such rules
            possible, but they will be of more interest to super nerds who are maintaining Lex-0 or
            those who are interested in extending it or customizing it further.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
