<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>The <hi rend="italic">Specification</hi> is the reference manual (and, effectively, the “grammar”) of TEI Lex-0. It tells you exactly which TEI constructs are in scope and how they are allowed to combine. When you need to answer questions like “Can this element go here?”, “Which attributes are permitted?”, or “What values are valid?”, the <hi rend="italic">Specification</hi> is the first place to look.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="italic">Specification</hi> is based on the TEI Lex-0 <hi rend="italic">schema</hi>: it lists the allowed <ref target="TEI.elements.html">elements</ref>, their attributes, and their content models (what may appear inside them), along with the reusable building blocks that make those content models manageable (<ref target="TEI.model-classes.html">model classes</ref>, <ref target="TEI.attribute-classes.html">attribute classes</ref>, <ref target="TEI.macros.html">macros</ref>, and <ref target="TEI.datatypes.html">data types</ref>). </p>
         <p>You do not need to read the <hi rend="italic">Specification</hi> front-to-back. Most encoders will use it as an aid: <list>
               <item><hi rend="bold">when choosing a tag</hi>: look up the element and read its definition and typical usage.</item>
               <item><hi rend="bold">when structuring entries</hi>: check an element’s content model to see what can go inside it.</item>
               <item><hi rend="bold">when validation fails</hi>: use the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Specification</hi> to understand what the schema expected at that
                  point.</item>
               <item><hi rend="bold">when mapping or converting data</hi>: the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Specification</hi> provides a stable target for transformation rules.</item>
               <item><hi rend="bold">when collaborating across projects</hi>: it helps you confirm that you are using the same constructs in the same way.</item>
            </list></p>
         <p>The <hi rend="italic">Specification</hi> is also the basis for the TEI Lex-0 <hi
               rend="italic">schema</hi> (<ref target="schema/lex0.rng">RNG</ref>, RNC, and XSD). These
            schemas are meant to be processed by computers and can be used to <hi rend="italic"
               >validate</hi> TEI Lex-0 documents for structural and attribute correctness. Do not
            try to read the schema, unless you suffer from insomnia.</p>
         <p>One important note: some recommendations in the narrative <hi rend="italic"
               >Guidelines</hi> (for example, <q>use this element only for X</q>, or <q>if you do A,
               you should also provide B</q>) may express semantic or project-policy constraints
            that are difficult to enforce automatically in a schema. In those cases, the narrative
            guidance remains essential even when the <hi rend="italic">Specification</hi> cannot
            “force” the rule. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>